Guide to the United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry Records, 1933-1974 UA.31.04.0011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry records
1933-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry
UA.31.04.0011
4.5 Linear Feet
The United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry coordinated and gathered the activities of the Methodist and Presbyterian student religious groups on campus. This collection contains papers and photographs relating to activities of Methodist and Presbyterian organizations at Duke University. The material ranges in date from 1933-1974, bulk from 1950-1974.
3600 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1980.
Historical Note
The United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry coordinated and gathered the activities of the Methodist and Presbyterian student religious groups on campus.
Methodist and Presbyterian religious groups have been, and continue to be, active in student life at Duke University. From the 1950s-1970s, groups like the Omega House, Westminster House, Methodist Student Center, and Celestial Omnibus Coffee House provided students with living and social activities on campus. They also gave students an opportunity to voice opinions on civil rights and the Vietnam War. It is unclear when or how the two religious student groups joined to form the United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry or when the joint venture ceased.
Today those activities are carried on by the Westminster Presbyterian Fellowship and Wesley Fellowship.
Collection Overview
This collection is divided into four series: organizations; writings; student protests and civil rights; and photographs and related material. The material ranges from 1933-1974, bulk 1950-1974.
Series one includes programs, minutes, charters, papers and posters from campus, chiefly from the Campus Church Relations Committee, Westminster Fellowship, United Ministry, University Christian Movement, Religious Life Council, United Campus Fellowship, Methodist Student Center, and Presbyterian Student Center. Notable inclusions are the architectural plans for the Westminster House and papers of the Celestial Omnibus Coffee House.
Series two includes essays, reprints, articles, texts, worship services, songs, and plays written by both staff and students.
Series three includes pamphlets, letters, and posters from the Civil Rights Movement and student protests of the Vietnam War. Chief among these materials are papers on the Duke Vigil following Martin Luther King Jr.'s death.
Series four is comprised of photographs and materials related to the campus religious organizations and students. These include photographs of the Wesley Players acting group, interest group sign-up sheets, and a memorial for student Nanci Weldon.
Related Material
Minister to the University (Dean of the Chapel) Records
Duke University Archives
Religious Life Reference Collection
Duke University Archives
Alice Mary Baldwin Papers
Duke University Archives
Methodist Student Center Records
Duke University Archives
Duke University -- Students -- Political activity; Duke University -- Students -- Religious activities; Duke University. United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry; Duke University. United Methodist-Presbyterian Ministry
- Organizations, 1.5 boxes
  - Presbyterian Christian Life Committee, 1970-1973 (Box 1)
  - Campus-Church Relations Committee,1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - Campus-Church Relations Committee,1962-1965 (Box 1)
  - Campus-Church Relations Committee,1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Campus-Church Relations Committee,1968 (Box 1)
  - Campus-Church Relations Committee,1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Campus-Church Relations Committee,1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Campus-Church Relations Board,1958-1963 (Box 1)
  - Westminster Fellowship Minutes and Merger Study, 1950-1957 (Box 1)
  - Westminster Fellowship, 1958-1962, Undated (Box 1)
  - Westminster Fellowship, 1964-1971, Undated (Box 1)
  - Westminster Fellowship Programs, 1957-1964 (Box 1)
  - Westminster Fellowship Programs, Undated (Box 1)
  - Westminster Fellowship Inventory of House Furnishings, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Westminster Fellowship House Design and Specifications (Box 1)
  - Westminster Fellowship Fundraising, 1962-1967 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement Working Papers, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement Working Papers, 1968 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement Working Papers, Undated (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement, 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement, Duke,1967 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement, Local,1966-1968 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement, Local, Charter and Position Papers,1968 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement, North Carolina, 1968 (Box 1)
  - University Christian Movement, National, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - United Ministry Papers, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - United Ministry Papers, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - United Ministry Papers, Undated (Box 1)
  - United Ministry Posters, Undated (Box 1)
  - United Ministry Self-Study, 1969-1971 (1 of 2) (Box 1)
  - United Ministry Self-Study, 1969-1971 (2 of 2) (Box 1)
  - United Campus Christian Fellowship, 1953-1966 (Box 1)
  - United Campus Christian Fellowship, 1967-1969, Undated (Box 1)
- Photographs and Related Material, 1 box
  - Methodist Center, 1968-1972 (Box 2)
  - Methodist Student Center, 1949-1955 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
  - Methodist Student Center, 1949-1955 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
  - Methodist Student Center, 1956-1974 (Box 2)
  - Methodist Center Insurance Papers, 1962-1971 (Box 2)
  - Specifications for the Methodist Student Center (Box 2)
  - Presbyterian Student Center HVAC Systems, 1963-1967 (Box 2)
  - Presbyterian Insurance Papers, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Religious Life Council, 1956-1965 (Box 2)
  - Religious Life Council, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
  - Methodist Student Felloship Report, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
  - Campus Ministry and ACT (Box 2)
  - Omega House, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
  - Community Two (Box 2)
  - House Church (Box 2)
  - Celestial Omnibus Coffee House, 1967-1969 (1 of 2) (Box 2)
  - Celestial Omnibus Coffee House, 1967-1969 (2 of 2) (Box 2)
  - Wesley Players, 1958-1960 (Box 2)
  - Jordan Building Board of Trustees Minutes, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Community of Lay Scholars, 1959-1963 (Box 2)
  - Summer Community Service, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Proposed Cooperation Between Methodists and Lutherans, 1964-1968 (Box 2)
  - Calendars of Duke Events, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - Nanci Weldon Memorial, 1965-1970 (Box 2)
  - Interest Groups: Sign-up Sheets, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Sorority Evaluation (Box 2)
  - [Unlabeled Folder] (Box 2)
  - Methodist Student Center Photographs, 1949-1958 (Box 2)
  - Wesley Players Photographs, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (1 of 11) (Box 2)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (2 of 11) (Box 2)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (3 of 11) (Box 2)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (4 of 11) (Box 2)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (5 of 11) (Box 2)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (6 of 11) (Box 2)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (7 of 11) (Box 2)
- Writings, 1 box
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (8 of 11) (Box 3)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (9 of 11) (Box 3)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (10 of 11) (Box 3)
  - Reprints, Essays, Articles, Texts (11 of 11) (Box 3)
  - Conference Programs (Box 3)
  - The Church and Higher Education (1 of 4) (Box 3)
  - The Church and Higher Education (2 of 4) (Box 3)
  - The Church and Higher Education (3 of 4) (Box 3)
  - The Church and Higher Education (4 of 4) (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
  - Mailing Lists (Box 3)
  - Ecumenical Conversations, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - Duke Chapel Wedding Service Information and Forms (Box 3)
  - The Challenger, 1959-1964 (Box 3)
  - Communications, 1968-1973 (Box 3)
  - Art Exhibitions (Box 3)
  - Concerning the Draft, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Poetry and Plays, 1933-1965 (Box 3)
  - Curious Kaleidoscope, 1973, Undated (Box 3)
  - Song Sheets, 1972-1974, Undated (Box 3)
  - Essays by Charles Johnson, 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - Spring Thing Report, 1972 (Box 3)
  - Human Sexuality Course Material, 1971, Undated (Box 3)
  - Worship Services and Papers, 1963-1973, Undated (Box 3)
  - World Student Christian Federation Publications, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Ecumenical Concerns, 1965-1969 (Box 3)
  - Program Materials, 1950-1964, Undated (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1962 (Box 3)
  - Motive Magazine Mailing Lists, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - New University Conference, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Magazine Clippings, 1960-1971 (Box 3)
- Student Protests and Civil Rights, .5 box
  - Civil Rights Movement Materials, 1961-1964 (Box 3)
  - Vietnam, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
  - Student Protests, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Duke Vigil, 1968 (1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Duke Vigil, 1968 (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Black Thursday - Black Students at Duke, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Poverty, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
  - Military and Moratorium, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Grape Workers Strike, Undated (Box 3)
  - Labor at Duke (Box 3)